Guide to the Florence and Henry Wald Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Florence and Henry Wald Papers
1955-2003
MS 1659
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
18
and 1.75 Gigabytes
The papers document the professional careers of Florence and Henry Wald, pioneers in the hospice movement. The collection includes records documenting the founding, planning, and inception of Hospice, Inc., the first hospice program in the United States. The Hospice, Inc. records also provide particularly useful documentation of an example of a community based institution that relied on grass roots support for its development and administration. Meticulous notes and other documentation Wald kept during the groundbreaking research, "A Nurse's Study of Care for Dying Papers," comprise another substantive part of the collection. Other papers include collected materials from several local, national, and international hospice groups, which document the integral role Wald and Hospice Inc. played within the broader context of the hospice movement. Writings of the Walds, and a small amount of material regarding the Yale University School of Nursing round out the collection.
Wald, Florence, 1917-2008
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Florence and Henry Wald, 1994. Gift of Florence Wald, 2001. Gift of Monica Mills, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
Patient information in Box 29 is restricted until January 1, 2050.
Researchers must sign the Access Agreement for the Florence Wald Notebooks to examine Series V, boxes 22-28.
Arrangement
Arranged in five series and two additions: I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979. II. Hospice Movement Subject Files, 1963-1980. III. Yale School of Nursing Files, 1956-1979. IV. Writings, 1955-1979. V. Research Notebooks, 1969-1971.
Scope and Contents
The papers document the professional careers of Florence and Henry Wald, pioneers in the hospice movement. The collection includes records documenting the founding, planning, and inception of Hospice, Inc., the first hospice program in the United States. The Hospice, Inc. records also provide particularly useful documentation of an example of a community based institution that relied on grass-roots support for its development and administration. Meticulous notes and other documentation Wald kept during the groundbreaking research, "A Nurse's Study of Care for Dying Papers," comprise another substantive part of the collection. Other papers include collected materials from several local, national, and international hospice groups, which document the integral role Wald and Hospice Inc. played within the broader context of the hospice movement. Writings of the Walds, and a small amount of material regarding the Yale University School of Nursing round out the collection.
Biographical / Historical
Born on April 19, 1917, in New York City, Florence Wald became a pioneer and a leading voice in the development of hospice care in the United States. Wald obtained a B.A. from Mount Holyoke College in 1938, an M.N. from the Yale University School of Nursing in 1941, and an M.S. from the Yale University Graduate School in 1956. From 1941 to 1943, she served as a staff nurse for the New York Visiting Nurse Service, from 1946 to 1952 she was a research assistant at the College of Physicians and Surgeons in New York City, and from 1955 to 1957, she was an instructor at Rutgers University School of Nursing. In 1957, Wald became a faculty member in the Yale University School of Nursing, where she has served as Assistant Professor, Associate Professor, Research Associate, Dean, and Clinical Professor.
In 1963, Wald met Cicely Saunders, the founder of the hospice movement in Great Britain and the director of St. Christopher's Hospice in London. During the second half of the 1960s, Wald and Saunders met several times in England and the United States and began to explore and conceptualize the possibilities of bringing hospice care to America. In late 1968, Wald began a two year grant supported study of dying patients. She set up an interdisciplinary team of health care providers and a spiritual advisor to care for the terminally ill. In exchange for care, the patients allowed the research team to keep notes to be used in determining the viability of developing an on-going hospice care program. The research developed into the beginning of institutionalized hospice care in the United States, and at the completion of the study, the group formed Hospice, Inc. and began planning a program and facility to provide hospice care in the New Haven area.
Florence Wald served on the Board of Directors and the planning staff for Hospice, Inc. until 1975, when she resigned due to internal conflicts. Upon her resignation, Wald was formally acknowledged as the Founder of Hospice, Inc. Wald continued to be an advocate for the hospice movement through publications, conference presentations, and consultant work, while she returned to teaching in the Yale School of Nursing. She participated in many national and international research groups within the hospice movement, most notably the International Work Group on Death, Dying, and Bereavement. Wald is the recipient of many honors, including honorary doctorates from Mount Holyoke College and the University of Bridgeport School of Nursing, the Founders Award from the National Hospice Organization, and the Contribution to Hospice Award from the National Association of Home Care. In 1998, she was inducted into the National Women's Hall of Fame.
As one of the original incorporators, Henry Wald also played a critical role in the founding of Hospice, Inc. He served as a member of the Board of Directors until 1977, and chaired the Building and Site Committee. As an architect and engineer who specialized in the design of health care facilities, he was instrumental in developing the facility of Hospice, Inc. in Branford, CT. Wald's 1971 thesis for his masters degree from the Columbia University School of Architecture, "A Hospice for Terminally Ill Patients," became a widely consulted source on the design of hospice care facilities. Henry Wald died on December 22, 2000. Florence Wald died on November 8, 2008, in her home in Branford, Connecticut.
Hospice care; Hospices (Terminal care); Nursing; Terminal care; Saunders, Cicely M., Dame; Wald, Florence, 1917-2008; Wald, Henry; Connecticut Hospice; Foundation of Thanatology; International Work Group on Death, Dying, and Bereavement; St. Christopher's Hospice; Yale University. School of Nursing
- Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  In November 1971, a group headed by Florence Wald formed Hospice, Inc. to provide care for the specialized needs of terminally ill patients and their families. Hospice, Inc. was the first organization of its kind in the United States, and it was modeled on St. Christopher's Hospice in London, England. In 1972, Hospice, Inc. started architectural planning, began raising funds, and developed guidelines for the selection of patients, staff, and volunteers. In 1973, the organization established the home care program, which began seeing patients in 1974. The inpatient program began seeing patients in 1979, with the completion of the hospice facility in Branford, CT. Also in 1979, Hospice, Inc. changed its name to Connecticut Hospice, Inc. to reflect that the organization provided care for the whole state of Connecticut. From its inception, the hospice has served as an education and research locus for the hospice movement, and it has hosted and participated in many national and international meetings and conferences. Researchers can find general overviews of the history of Hospice, Inc. under "Clippings," "Kerns, Larry," and "Newsletters."
  The series documents the founding, planning, growth, and administration of Hospice, Inc. Arranged alphabetically by subject and type of material, the files include correspondence, memoranda, reports, budgets, minutes, clippings, newsletters, task force and committee records, and other miscellaneous materials. The bulk of the materials range from 1971 to 1975, the time in which Florence Wald worked for Hospice, Inc. Files which document Wald's 1975 resignation can be found under "Wald, Florence."
  The administrative records of the institution are scattered throughout the series. Records of the Board of Directors provide an overview of the hospice through reports and meeting minutes. Folders listed under the Home Care Program, Inpatient Care Program, Committees and Task Forces sections give a more detailed view of the functioning of each of the various parts of the organization. Folders filed under "Case support of Hospice, Inc." and "Task Forces-Philosophy and Internal Organization" document discussions concerning the vision and goals of Hospice, Inc..
  The planning and construction of the physical plant for Hospice, Inc. is recorded in several files, including "Architectural planning," "Chan, Lo-yi [hospice architect]," "Committees-Building," "Inpatient Care Program-Facilities," "Task forces-Building," and "Wald, Henry." Similarly, financial records of the organization are spread between the Finances and Fund-raising sections and the "Committees-Development" and "Task Forces-Finance" folders.
  The series also documents the educational role in the hospice movement that Hospice, Inc. and its staff played. Records of the research conference "Interdisciplinary Study of a Dying Patient" include early discussions between Hospice staff and advisors, including Cicely Saunders, which were used in founding Hospice, Inc. The "Colloquia on the Humanities and Death" folders contain materials documenting a series of conferences sponsored by the hospice. Related materials on hospice education and research can be found throughout Series II.
  - Appointment book, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Architectural planning, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 2 - 5)
  - Board of Directors
    - Annual reports, 1973-1977 (Box 1, Folder 6 - 7)
    - By-laws, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Minutes and memoranda, 1971-1973 (Box 1, Folder 9 - 11)
    - Minutes and memoranda, 1974-1978, undated (Box 2, Folder 12 - 21)
  - Building site, Hamden, CT [not used], 1973, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Case for support of Hospice, Inc. ["To Honor All Life"], 1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Chan, Lo-yi [hospice architect], 1973-1977, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Clippings [miscellaneous], 1971-1975, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Colloquia on the Humanities and Death [sponsored by Hospice, Inc.]
    - General, 1976-1978 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Papers given, 1976-1979, undated (Box 3, Folder 27 - 29)
  - Commission on Hospitals and Health Care, State of Connecticut, 1973-1974, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Committees
    - General, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Building, 1976-1978, undated (Box 3, Folder 32 - 33)
      General note
      See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 75
    - Development, 1975-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Executive, 1971, 1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Joint Conference, 1974-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 36 - 40)
    - Licensing, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 41)
    - Medical Advisory, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
    - Staff Selection, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 43)
    - Steering, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 44)
    - Structure, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Communication, 1974-1977, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Connecticut Hospital Association Group Purchasing Organization, 1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Connecticut regulations re: hospices, 1971-1978, undated (Box 4, Folder 48 - 49)
  - "Days Away" [retreats], 1973-1975 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Diagnostic Radiation Unit Program, 1974-1975, undated (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Education Resource Center [Henry J. Kaiser Family Foundation Grant], 1974, 1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Finances
    - Budgets, 1971-1978, undated (Box 5, Folder 53 - 55)
      See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 110-112
    - Reports and statements, 1973-1977, undated (Box 5, Folder 56 - 61)
  - Flow charts, 1972-1974, undated (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Fundraising
    - General, 1971-1978, undated (Box 6, Folder 63 - 66)
    - Foundations, 1971-1975, undated (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Funeral information, 1975-1976, undated (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Health care statistics and charts, 1969-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Home Care Program
    - General, 1973-1977, undated (Box 6, Folder 70 - 71)
    - Patient information, 1974-1975, undated
      See: Restricted Files Folder 1
    - Proposals, 1972-1975 (Box 6, Folder 72)
    - Staff recruitment, 1971-1975, undated (Box 6, Folder 73 - 74)
  - Inpatient Care Program
    - Facilities committee, 1973-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 75)
      See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 32-33
    - Food service, 1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 76)
  - In-service education, undated (Box 7, Folder 77)
    See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 50
  - Insurance reimbursement, 1971-1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 78)
  - "Interdisciplinary Study of a Dying Patient" [Research conference], 1970-1971 (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Kerns, Larry, "The Study of the Creation of a Community Setting: Hospice", 1975 (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Membership lists, 1973, undated (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Memoranda [miscellaneous], 1971-1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - National Advisory Council of Hospice, Inc., 1974, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - National Institutes of Health, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - New York State Hospice Demonstration Program, 1978 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Newsletter, 1973-1979, undated (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Notes [miscellaneous], 1972-1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Opening of Hospice, Inc., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Personnel, 1973-1976, undated (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Planning, 1970-1975, undated (Box 7, Folder 90 - 91)
  - Planning staff, 1972-1975 (Box 8, Folder 92 - 94)
  - Policy statements, 1972-1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - Progress report and program plan, 1973 (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Public Information Director, 1975-1976, undated (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Public relations, 1972-1978, undated (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Public Works Bill, Branford, CT, 1976-1977, undated (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Staff meetings, 1973-1974, undated (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Staff recruitment, 1972-1975, undated (Box 8, Folder 101 - 102)
    See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 73 - 74
  - Task forces
    - General, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 103)
    - Building, 1971-1978, undated (Box 9, Folder 104 - 108)
    - Community Relations, 1972-1975, 1979, undated (Box 9, Folder 109)
    - Finance, 1972-1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 110 - 112)
      General
      See also: Series I. Hospice, Inc. Files, 1968-1979 Folder 53 - 55
    - Patient Care, 1971-1974, undated (Box 9, Folder 113 - 114)
    - Philosophy and Internal Organization, 1971-1975, undated (Box 10, Folder 115 - 117)
    - Professional Relations, 1972-1975, undated (Box 10, Folder 118)
    - Research, 1972-1975, 1977, undated (Box 10, Folder 119)
  - Wald, Florence
    - Correspondence, 1973-1974, 1977-1978, undated (Box 10, Folder 120)
    - Resignation from Hospice, Inc., 1975-1979, undated (Box 10, Folder 121 - 122)
  - Wald, Henry [correspondence, clippings, and notes], 1968-1978, undated (Box 10, Folder 123 - 126)
- Hospice Movement Subject Files, 1963-1980; Series II
  Arranged alphabetically, the Hospice Movement Subject Files are comprised of correspondence, newsletters, brochures, clippings, writings, and other miscellanea pertaining to other hospices and to the hospice movement in general. The materials in the series represent a cross-section of the hospice movement and place the activities of Hospice, Inc. into the broader context of hospice work on national and international levels.
  Florence Wald's interactions with hospice pioneer Cicely Saunders can be found under files for St. Christopher's Hospice. These files include correspondence and notes Wald took on visits to St. Christopher's while conducting initial research on hospices. Notes that Wald recorded while visiting other English hospice sites can be found under files for the Copper Cliffs Nursing Home, Douglas MacMillan Home, St. Barabas' House, and St. Luke's Nursing Home. Wald and Saunders' collaboration and active participation in the International Work Group on Death, Dying, and Bereavement, the Foundation of Thanatology and the International Seminars on Terminal Care are also documented in the series.
  The series also contains files documenting Wald's participation in several national organizations dealing with hospice issues such as the Association of Community Cancer Centers, the National Hospice Organization, the National Institute for the Seriously Ill and Dying, and the National Cancer Institute.
  Additional files reflect Florence Wald's position as a consultant and contact person for individual hospices. Files for Hospice Buffalo, Inc., Hillhaven Foundation, Hospice Rhode Island, Hospice of Seattle, Kaiser Permanente Medical Care Program of Southern California, and Riverside Hospice contain extensive reports made to the National Cancer Institute in preparation for site visits made by Florence Wald. Materials pertaining to other hospices and hospice groups include newsletters, correspondence, reports, and brochures. Miscellaneous "Bibliographies," "Brochures," "Clippings," and "Newsletters," also document the hospice movement on local and national levels.
  - Alexian Brothers' Workshop [St. Louis, MO], 1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - American Nurses Association, 1978, undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - American Oncologic Hospital [Philadelphia, PA], 1977, undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Association of Community Cancer Centers [Washington, DC], 1979 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Benedictine Sisters [Mt. Angel, OR], 1975 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Bibliographies [miscellaneous], 1965-1971 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Brochures [miscellaneous], 1977-1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Butterfly Hill [Paoli, PA], 1973-1976, undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Calvary Hospital [Bronx, NY], 1973, undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Clippings [miscellaneous], 1963-1979, undated (Box 11, Folder 10 - 16)
  - Community Health Center [New Haven, CT; development plan], 1973 (Box 11, Folder 17)
  - Concern for Dying [New York, NY], 1978 (Box 12, Folder 18)
  - Connecticut Hospital Association, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 19)
  - Connecticut Regional Medical Program, 1970-1975 (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Copper Cliffs Nursing Home [Brighton, England], 1975, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
  - Davies-McKegney Study on Death and Dying, 1968, undated (Box 12, Folder 22)
  - The Douglas McMillan Home [Stoke on Trent, England], 1972-1975, undated (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - ELM Services, Inc., Hospice Development and Technical Assistance Group, undated (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Forbes Hospice [Pittsburgh, PA], 1978, undated (Box 12, Folder 25)
  - Foundation of Thanatology [New York, NY]
    - General, 1973-1979, undated (Box 12, Folder 26 - 29)
    - Publicity packet, undated (Box 12, Folder 30)
  - Hartford [CT] Consortium cancer case, 1979 (Box 13, Folder 31)
  - Harvard University/Massachusetts Institute of Technology [architecture course taught by Lo-Yi Chan], 1976-1977 (Box 13, Folder 32)
  - Hastings Center, Institute of Society, Ethics, and the Life Sciences, 1975-1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 33)
  - Hillhaven Foundation [Tacoma, WA]
    - General, 1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 34)
    - Proposals, 1976 (Box 13, Folder 35)
  - Hillhaven Hospice [Tucson, AZ], 1977-1978, undated (Box 13, Folder 36)
  - Horizons in the Life Cycle [New York, NY], 1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 37)
  - Hospice Buffalo, Inc. [NY], 1976, undated (Box 13, Folder 38 - 40)
  - Hospice Care of Mid-America [Kansas City, MO], 1977-1979, undated (Box 13, Folder 41)
  - Hospice Care of Rhode Island [Providence, RI], 1976-1979, undated (Box 13, Folder 42 - 43)
  - Hospice Institute for Education, Training and Research [New Haven, CT], 1977-1980, undated (Box 13, Folder 44)
  - Hospice Maran Atha [Spokane, WA], 1977-1978, undated (Box 13, Folder 45)
  - Hospice of Marin [Kentfield, CA], 1975, undated (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - Hospice of Massachusetts [Boston, MA], undated (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - Hospice of Santa Barbara [CA], 1976-1978, n.d (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - Hospice of Seattle [WA], 1976, undated (Box 14, Folder 49 - 50)
  - Hospice of Westchester [White Plains, NY], 1975-1979, undated (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - International Seminar on Terminal Care, McGill University [Montreal, Canada], 1976 (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - [Second] International Seminar on Terminal Care, Royal Victoria Hospital [Montreal, Canada], 1978, undated (Box 14, Folder 53)
  - International Work Group on Death, Dying and Bereavement
    - General, 1974-1979, undated (Box 14, Folder 54 - 59)
    - Bibliographies, 1975-1978, undated (Box 14, Folder 60)
    - Conferences and meetings
      - Asilomar, 1976-1978, undated (Box 15, Folder 61)
      - Cantrakon, 1978-1979, undated (Box 15, Folder 62)
      - Montreal, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 63)
      - Yale University, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 64)
  - Kaiser Permanente Medical Care Program, Southern California Region, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 65 - 66)
  - Kron, Joan, "Designing a Better Place to Die", 1976 (Box 15, Folder 67)
  - Lefkowitz, Nathan [writings], 1972-1977, undated (Box 15, Folder 68)
  - Lombardi Cancer Research Center, Georgetown University [Washington, DC], 1978, undated (Box 15, Folder 69)
  - Lukawsky, Alexandra, "The Viability of the Hospice Program of Care Within the American Medical System", 1979 (Box 15, Folder 70 - 71)
  - Lutheran Medical Center [St. Louis, MO], 1977-1978 (Box 15, Folder 72)
  - Make Today Count [Burlington, IA], 1975 (Box 15, Folder 73)
  - Mercy Hospital [Rockville, Centre, NY], 1978 (Box 15, Folder 74)
  - Ministers in Medical Education, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 75)
  - National Cancer Institute, 1976-1978, undated (Box 15, Folder 76)
  - National Hospice Organization, 1975-1980, undated (Box 16, Folder 77)
  - National Institute for the Seriously Ill and Dying [Philadelphia, PA], 1976-1977, undated (Box 16, Folder 78)
  - Newsletters [miscellaneous], 1978-1979, undated (Box 16, Folder 79)
  - Nursing homes, 1976-1977, undated (Box 16, Folder 80)
  - Parkwood Community Hospital, Hospice Care Unit [Canoga Park, NY], 1976-1977, undated (Box 16, Folder 81)
  - Pasadena Hospice Inland Association [CA], 1977, undated (Box 16, Folder 82)
  - Pennsylvania Hospital [Philadelphia], 1978, undated (Box 16, Folder 83)
  - Project One, Waterbury Hospital Health Center [Waterbury, CT], 1976-1977, undated (Box 16, Folder 84)
  - Project Support, Morris County Guidance Committee [Mountain Lakes, NJ], 1975-1976, undated (Box 16, Folder 85)
  - Riverside Hospice [Boonton Township, NJ], 1976-1979, undated (Box 16, Folder 86 - 87)
  - St. Barabas' House [Worthing, England], 1973-1977-1979, undated (Box 16, Folder 88)
  - St. Christopher's Hospice [Sydenham, England]
    - General, 1966-1979, undated (Box 17, Folder 89 - 93)
    - Photographs, 1973, undated (Box 17, Folder 94 - 95)
  - St. John's Hospital [Springfield, IL], 1978 (Box 17, Folder 96)
  - St. Luke's Hospital Center [New York, NY], 1975-1976, undated (Box 17, Folder 97)
  - St. Luke's Nursing Home [Sheffield, England], 1973-1974, undated (Box 17, Folder 98)
  - Saunders, Cicely
    See: Series II. Hospice Movement Subject Files, 1963-1980 Folder 54 - 59
    See: Series II. Hospice Movement Subject Files, 1963-1980 Folder 89 - 93
  - Shanti Nilaya [Escondida, CA], 1977-1979, undated (Box 17, Folder 99)
  - United States, Department of Health, Education, and Welfare, 1970, 1975-1979, undated (Box 17, Folder 100 - 102)
  - United States, Veterans Administration, 1978-1979, undated (Box 17, Folder 103)